<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London at Guild-Hall Chappel, on Easter-day, 1689 / by Tho. Mariott ...</title>
            <author>Mariott, Thomas, d. 1708?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12272228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12272228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58299</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58299)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 988:15, 1508:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London at Guild-Hall Chappel, on Easter-day, 1689 / by Tho. Mariott ...</title>
                  <author>Mariott, Thomas, d. 1708?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York, and Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Easter --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:58299:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Pilkington Mayor, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <date>Martis <hi>xvi.</hi> die April. <hi>1689.</hi> Anno<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regni Regis &amp; Reginae <hi>WILL.</hi> &amp; <hi>MARIAE</hi> Angl. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Primo.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Mariott</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, on <hi>Eaſter-Day</hi> laſt, before the Lord Mayor, and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagstaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 26. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Carolus Alſton,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Hen.</hi> Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58299:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honourable THE Lord Mayor AND ALDER MEN OF THE CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At GUILD-HALL Chappel, on <hi>Eaſter-Day,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. MARIOTT,</hi> M. A. and Rector of <hi>Little Canfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58299:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58299:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Sir Thomas Pilkington, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lord Mayor OF THE CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS your favourable Acceptance of this Diſcourſe was more than I could reaſonably expect, being conſcious to my ſelf of my own Weakneſs: ſo, your Command is the only reaſon of its appearing in publick. There is ſometimes <hi>a Reſurrection of the Body Politick,</hi> when it hath been as it were dead and buried <hi>under Oppreſſion and Tyranny,</hi> which our Nation (through the Infinite Mercy, and by the
<pb facs="tcp:58299:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Almighty Power of God) hath lately Experienced; a Mercy not only above our Deſerts, but Hopes: of which I am aſſured, not only <hi>your Lordſhip,</hi> but all <hi>True Proteſtants</hi> are deeply ſenſible; and for which they are heartily thankful. But it is <hi>another Reſurrection</hi> which is here treated of, the Reſurrection <hi>of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Mankind,</hi> and of our own Bodies by vertue of his: no circumſtantial, indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent point, but the great Fundamental of our Chriſtian Religion, and in that reſpect (I hope) of more general uſe. That you may have part, with all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in this Reſurrection at the laſt Day to Immortality and Glory, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of your Lord in Everlaſting Bliſs, is, and always ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt obliged and obedient Servant, <hi>THO. MARIOTT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58299:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN xx. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For as yet they knew not the Scripture, That he muſt riſe again from the dead.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are part of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by our Church, for this Day; guiding us to ſpeak concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lofty Myſtery of Chriſt's Reſurrection; <hi>Eaſter-Day</hi> being kept by our Church, as a ſolemn Feſtival Day, and day of Rejoycing for the Miracle of Chriſt's riſing from the dead. Among our Feſtivals this ſeems to carry the brighteſt ſplendour of Antiquity upon it, it having been the practice of the Church from the Apoſtles days downward, to keep this day in a more than ordinary ſolemn
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58299:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>manner. It is the opinion of no mean Divines, that what the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians, Let us keep the Feaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7, 8.</note> doth look to the ſpecial and Religious Solemnization of the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> having immediately before made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of Chriſt our Paſsover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great difference there was among the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians about <hi>Eaſter,</hi> but this, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the time, not the thing.</hi> Some kept the <hi>Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</hi> or <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at the ſame time as the <hi>Jews</hi> kept theirs; others afterwards, ſo that this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned no ſmall ſtir in the Church: yet here it may not be unworthy of your obſervation, that although they differed in their Opinion and Practice,<note place="margin">Of the time of keeping <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Vid. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. cont. Haereſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>cont. Sect. Audiano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </note> concerning this particular, the Eaſtern Church keeping <hi>Eaſter</hi> with the Jews before the <hi>Spring Solſtice,</hi> the Weſtern Church after the <hi>Spring Solſtice,</hi> or <hi>Equinoctial;</hi> they did not in the early days, next the Apoſtles, ſeparate from each other, but, as occaſion ſerved, Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated together. This point was in <hi>the Council of Nice</hi> determined, that the Chriſtians ſhould not ſymbolize with the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor with them keep the Paſsover before the <hi>Spring Solſtice,</hi> or <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> which was afterwards confirmed by the <hi>Synod of Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syn. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och. Can. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and ſo this difference was compoſed. <hi>And I pray God ſend us as happy a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58299:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of theſe unhappy differences at this day among Proteſtants, as there was in the Primitive Church of the difference relating to the Feaſt of Eaſter.</hi> By what hath been ſaid of this early difference in the ancient Church, concerning the time of keeping <hi>Eaſter;</hi> it is ſo much the more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it always hath been the practice of the Univerſal Chriſtian Church, to keep <hi>Eaſter Day</hi> with a ſpecial Solemnity, in memory of Chriſt's Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>It was no ordinary Piety, ſtrictneſs, devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with which the Primitive Chriſtians were wont to keep this Solemnity, by extraordinary faſting ſometime before, the better to humble their Souls for their Sins, and prepare them for ſo joyful a Feaſt; and great things do they ſpeak of this day. A Great Council calls it,<note place="margin">ſyn. <hi>6.</hi> in Trullo. Can. <hi>90, 91.</hi> Greg. Naz. Orat. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The great Sabbath. Gregory Nazianzen</hi> calls it, <hi>The Feaſt of Feaſts, and Solemnity of Solemnities, as much excelling the reſt of the Feaſts, as the Sun doth the reſt of the Stars.</hi> And in the ſame Oration calls it, <hi>the greateſt of days.</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> goes ſo far as to tell us,<note place="margin">S. Chryſoſt. Tom. <hi>5.</hi> Serm. <hi>34.</hi> de Reſur. Chriſti.</note> that this Solemnity is not only a Feaſt on Earth, but a Feaſt in Heaven. <hi>To day</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking of <hi>Eaſter-Day</hi>) <hi>there is Joy on Earth, to day there is Joy in Heaven:</hi> And he gives this reaſon of it, <hi>For if there be Joy in Earth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58299:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Heaven, for one Sinner that repenteth; how much more will there be Joy in Heaven on this Day, when the</hi> whole World <hi>was extorted out of the hands of the Devil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the Birth of Chriſt, the World began to expect great things from a perſon ſo born and attended with ſuch notable Signs and Wonders; and ſtill as he grew up, and gave Evidence of his Vertue and Power, the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of men were more raiſed and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: But when he began to Preach, and work ſuch mighty Miracles as he did, how muſt Mens Hearts be affected and filled with hopes of great deſigns to be carried on by ſuch a Perſon? but ſee how the Scene was altered, a little while was it, and he on whom all their Eyes and Hearts were fixed, was betrayed; by the vulgar abuſed, by the Governours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, by their Inſtruments Executed, his Hands and Feet nailed to the Croſs; the Sun was under a Cloud, the object of the Worlds Hopes and Joy expired, gave up the Ghoſt, died, was buried, and lay for a while in the Grave, as other weak frail Mortals. What a diſappointment this was, and how they did lament it, you may partly ſee by the Speech of the two Men going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>We truſted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58299:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that it had been he which ſhould have redeemed Iſrael; and beſides all this, to day is the third day ſince theſe things were done:</hi> by which it doth appear, how the Friends of Chriſt were pierced in his pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and their hopes buried in his Sepulchre. <hi>Bleſſed Day</hi> was it now when the Lord aroſe, the <hi>Sun,</hi> though ſet a while, appeared again: a new Face came upon the World, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were brought under a Cloud, the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Friends of Chriſt revived, their hope before (as it were) dead and buried, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain raiſed together with their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who roſe again, according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, though for a while, even the Diſciples themſelves underſtood not thoſe places, which ſpake of his Reſurrection. <hi>For as yet they knew not the Scripture, That he muſt riſe again from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to that part of the Text which relates unto the Diſciples not knowing the Scriptures, at that time which referred unto Chriſt's Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: We might from thence draw ſeveral Obſervations not unuſeful for us, but that we purpoſe to apply our ſelves wholly to the point of the Reſurrection, the proper ſubject of the Day; concerning which, we conſider three things.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58299:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>That according to the Scripture, Chriſt was to riſe from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That Chriſt did truly and really riſe from the dead, according as the Scripture had foretold:</hi> for this is that which Saint <hi>John</hi> believed, and which he doth deſignedly prove in this place.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>That there was a neceſſity Chriſt ſhould riſe again from the dead;</hi> which you have in the word <hi>muſt:</hi> for ſo the Scripture did declare, that he <hi>muſt</hi> riſe again from the dead.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt thing we enter upon, is to ſhow, <hi>That according to the Scripture, the Meſſiah was to riſe from the dead.</hi> The Types in Scripture are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to this purpoſe. So long ago as <hi>Adam</hi> this was typified, of whom we read, that ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Creation he was caſt into a deep ſleep, whilſt the Woman was taken out of his ſide, and then <hi>awaked again:</hi> Thus the <hi>Second Adam Chriſt,</hi> of whom the firſt was a type, ſlept the ſleep of Death, and ſleeping, his ſide was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whereout came Water and Blood (which gave being to his Spouſe the Church) and then after a while he <hi>awoke,</hi> revived, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>You read how <hi>Iſaac</hi> was laid upon the Altar with the Wood: Now <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Sacrificing his Son thus in Will, was a type of God's giving
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58299:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Son to be a Sacrifice in very deed: but <hi>Iſaac</hi> for all this, came off, and was preſerved alive; a Figure, <hi>that our Iſaac the Lord Jeſus,</hi> though really ſacrificed, yet ſhould riſe again, and Death ſhould have no power over him.</p>
            <p>Many were the Conflicts of <hi>Sampſon</hi> with the Philiſtins, vanquiſhing them time after time; of whom we read how he carried away the Gates of <hi>Gaza,</hi> Poſts and all, up to a high Hill; in all this a type of Chriſt, who was to have many ſharp conflicts with the World and the Devil for us, and that he ſhould at the laſt, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away the Gates of Hell and Death, that none could hold him. Sad was the condition of <hi>Jonas</hi> when he fled to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> when followed with a Tempeſt, when caſt into the Sea, when in the Jaws of the Whale, when in the Whales Belly, but yet he gets out in a ſmall time, and appears again upon dry land. What was this but a type of Chriſt coming to <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> in his Nativity, followed with a perpetual and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtorm in the Ocean of this World all the while he lived, ſwallowed up of Death, lying in the Grave, and riſing again the third day? Truth it ſelf ſo expounds it, we may believe him.</p>
            <p>Beſides which Scripture-types, many are the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58299:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Scripture-Prophecies that Chriſt ſhould riſe from the dead. The firſt Scripture which gives no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of a Chriſt, doth not only mention him as ſuffering and dying, but as riſing, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious. If <hi>Thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> noted his ſufferings; yet, <hi>He ſhall bruiſe thy head,</hi> was a Prophecy of his Victory, and made good when he roſe from the dead. When the Patriarch <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> bleſſed his Sons, he thus Propheſieth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.9.</note> Judah <hi>is a Lions Whelp, from the prey, my Son, thou art gone up, he ſtooped down, he couched as a Lion, who ſhall rouze him up? Judah</hi> was the Tribe of which Chriſt came; and here is, even by the Confeſſion of the Jewiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors themſelves, a Prophecy of the Meſſiah: <hi>Chriſt</hi> it is that is here reſembled unto the Lions Whelp: in that it is ſaid, he ſtooped down, he couched, therein is ſet forth his ſuffering, when he bowed the Head, and gave up the Ghoſt: but this <hi>Lion</hi> is rouzed, and there's the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Reſurrection, and in that it is ſaid, <hi>Who ſhall rouze him up?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſid. Hiſp. Com. in Gen.</note> thereby is noted (as <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> expounds) that no Man ſhould do this but himſelf. When <hi>Balaam</hi> Propheſied of a <hi>Star</hi> that ſhould ariſe out of <hi>Jacob,</hi> he plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, not only the ſetting of this Star in his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but the riſing of it again when he came
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58299:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of the Grave. And if the Book of <hi>Job</hi> was written by <hi>Moſes</hi> (as the learned conclude) then <hi>Job</hi>'s ſaying,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. p.</hi> 17. ſeveral te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies.</note> 
               <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth,</hi> is another Prophecy out of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Writings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt's Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>From the Writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> let us proceed to the Book of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> where, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee,</hi> is undoubtedly a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of the Reſurrection of the Meſſiah; for ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> interprets it, and ſhows, that hereby was declared and manifeſted, on the day of his Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Act. 13.33.</note> That <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the true and eternal Son of the moſt high God. And, as when it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſ. 110.7.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall drink of the brook in the way,</hi> his Sufferings are foretold: So, when it is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall lift up the head,</hi> his Reſurrection is ſignified unto us. And again,<note place="margin">Pſ. 16.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou wilt not leave my Soul in Hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption,</hi> is a clear place to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for <hi>David</hi> cannot herein ſpeak of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who died and ſaw Corruption, as others; but he doth foretel how Chriſt, that holy one, ſhould not lie in the Grave till he ſaw corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as others: nor his Soul continue in Hell, but his Soul ſhould be brought back, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto his Body, and his Body raiſed out of the Grave. And in another place, where the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58299:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>I am as a man that hath no ſtrength,</hi> thereby is noted the ſuffering of Chriſt, and his lying in the Grave; but then the following words, <hi>free among the dead,</hi> do ſhow his riſing again from the dead; for he is ſaid to be free among the dead,<note place="margin">S. Cyp. in Symb. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt.</note> becauſe he could not be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of death, as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> expounds it.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaias</hi> in many places ſpeaks of Chriſt's Reſurrection; for whenas he brings him in born in this manner, <hi>Unto us a Child is born, unto us a Son is given,</hi> and then afterwards ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6, 7.</note> that <hi>Of the increaſe of his Government and Peace there ſhall be no end:</hi> he doth ſuppoſe his riſing from the dead, for had he continued in the Grave, there had been an end of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and therefore did he deſcribe him by the name <hi>Wonderful,</hi> not only in reſpect of the wonderfulneſs of his Nativity and Death, but becauſe of the wonderfulneſs of his riſing out of the Grave. And when the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, having ſpoken at large of his Sufferings, his Death, and Burial, doth tell us, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.10.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhould ſee his ſeed, and prolong his days;</hi> it hath a neceſſary reference to his Reſurrection. Nay, ſo punctual are the Writings of the Prophets, that they foretel the very time when Chriſt ſhould riſe, even on <hi>the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58299:8"/>third day. After two days will he revive us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>in the third day will he raiſe us up, and we ſhall live in his ſight.</hi> And in that the Prophet ſpeaks in the plural number, it refers to thoſe alſo who did riſe with Chriſt, and attended upon him for the greater Solemnity of this day. By all which we ſee, that according to the Scriptures, Chriſt was to riſe again. I proceed now to</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond point, which is to ſhew, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt the Son of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>who was Crucified and Buried by the Jews, did moſt really and truly riſe again from the dead, according as theſe and many other Scriptures had foretold.</hi> Let us ſee what Witneſſes we can produce to prove this. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame day he roſe, he appeared ſeveral times to ſeveral perſons. Firſt to <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> then to <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> and the other <hi>Mary,</hi> as they were going together from the Sepulchre, then to the two Diſciples going to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> then unto St. <hi>Peter</hi> alone by himſelf, then unto the Diſciples as they were together, <hi>Thomas</hi> being abſent. To theſe add his Apparitions at ſeveral other times. Eight days after his Reſurrection, he appeared to his Diſciples, <hi>Thomas</hi> being preſent: After this to ſeven of his Diſciples as they were fiſhing at the Sea of <hi>Tiberias:</hi> Again unto the eleven Diſciples as they were upon a Mount of <hi>Galilee.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58299:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>He appeared unto above five hundred of the Brethren at once, after that he was ſeen of <hi>James</hi> apart. The day of his Aſcenſion he was ſeen to the Apoſtles on the Mount of <hi>Olivet,</hi> when he was taken up into Heaven; Laſtly, He was ſeen of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> and theſe were Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes choſen before of God to bear record of his Reſurrection, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us. True Witneſſes were they, no Deceivers, as the Keepers of the Sepulchre falſly reported, ſaying, <hi>His Diſciples came by night, and ſtole him away whilſt we ſlept.</hi> See what an unhappy Dilemma St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth run theſe Keepers into: either it was falſe that they ſlept, and ſo, Liers are not to be believed: or it was true, and then how could they tell what happened? Fooliſh mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if they were awake, why did they ſuffer it? If they were aſleep, how did they know it? Enough is there in the ſtory to evince their Falſity, and to clear the Diſciples Innocency. And in that Chriſt was not ſeen to one alone, but to ſeveral together, even to a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, it ſhows they could not be deceived in this matter. If any one ſhall ſay, theſe were his Diſciples and Friends, and therefore their teſtimonies not full enough to ſettle our Faith in this point, to theſe we might add the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58299:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Enemies. Let <hi>Pilate</hi> be the firſt, who was the Man that delivered him to the Jews to be Crucified;<note place="margin">Vit. <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii.</hi>
               </note> for after theſe things thus paſſed in <hi>Judea, Pilate,</hi> who was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> under the Roman Emperour, wrote Letters unto <hi>Tiberius</hi> (in whoſe Reign Chriſt was Crucified) wherein he advertiſed the Emperour of the Death of Chriſt, of the manner of it, of the Miracles he had done in his Life, as alſo of his Reſurrection, to the end that he ſhould adviſe and determine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt ſhould not be held as a God, and worſhipped as a God. So that here is the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Pilate</hi> to the Reſurrection, who, no doubt, being their Chief Governour, had the beſt means to inform himſelf of the truth. To this add the teſtimony of the Watch. Theſe, moſt likely, were choice buſy Fellows pickt out on purpoſe for ſuch a deſign, (as let the deſign be never ſo bad, ſome will be found to carry it on) and what ſay they?<note place="margin">Mat. 28.11.</note> 
               <hi>Some of the watch came unto the City, and ſhowed unto the chief Prieſts all the things that were done.</hi> They came, as it were, thunder ſtruck, looking like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ghoſts, with their hair ſtanding an end, and tell all the ſtory of the Angels deſcending and rolling away the Stone, and Chriſt's riſing; for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58299:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>this is that which was done, and this is that they tell them: which was ſo plain, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could the Chief Prieſts any way reſiſt the Evidence, but only through deſperate wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hire the Souldiers, with money, to blaze a notorious lie to cheat the common people with. So that here is the expreſs teſtimony of the Watch, and the implicit teſtimony of the High-Prieſts themſelves, to the truth of Chriſt's Reſurrection. And was not <hi>Saul,</hi> (afterwards called <hi>Paul</hi>) for ſome time, a notorious Enemy of Chriſt? yet afterwards proved he a moſt couragious Witneſs of his Reſurrection? Now, though the Friends of Chriſt might have been ſuppoſed not to ſpeak the truth, yet, when his moſt deſperate Enemies witneſs the ſame, it muſt be acknowledged, that Chriſt did accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture, riſe again from the dead. If ſuch a multitude of Earthly Witneſſes, Men, Women, Rich, Poor, Friends, Foes, Jews, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, be not enough; yet at leaſt the teſtimony of Heavenly Angels ought to be believed. Whoſe are thoſe words? <hi>He is not here, but is riſen:</hi> are they not the words of a Heavenly Angel? and, if it may be more convincing, St. <hi>Luke</hi> makes mention of two Angels who aſſert this: though theſe be enough, yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58299:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>we add to theſe the teſtimony of the Spirit ſent down upon the Apoſtles, on purpoſe to impower them to be Witneſſes unto the Reſurrection of Chriſt through the World.</p>
            <p>And who can think all this ſhould be to give teſtimony to a Reſurrection that was not every way true and real? Some Hereticks in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times, had the impudence ſo to teach,<note place="margin">Againſt this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Vid. <hi>Aug. lib. de Agone Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano. cap.</hi> 24.</note> that as Chriſt died in appearance only, ſo he did riſe only in appearance; it will therefore be convenient in this place to ſhow, that Chriſt did truly and really riſe from the dead in the very ſame Body, Fleſh, and Bones, which was Crucified, and what ever tended to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the human nature. Thoſe unto whom he appeared,<note place="margin">Aq. p. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>55.</hi> a. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> knew him to be the ſame who had converſed with them before. The verity of Chriſt's Reſurrection, doth <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſhow by many Arguments, both in reſpect of his Body and Soul. That it was a true ſolid Body in which he roſe, no fantaſtick, aerial Body, is evident, becauſe he offer'd it to be ſeen and felt; now, a Spirit hath no Fleſh and Bones, as they ſaw and felt he had. And that it was a true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Body, was evident to them all by the ſhape of it. And that it was the very ſame
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58299:11"/>humane Body in which he lived and died, he evidenced by ſhe wing them the prints of the Nails in his Hands and Feet, and of the Spear in his ſide. If any wonder at this, that Chriſt ſhould riſe again from the dead with Scars, they are to know, that this was not for any weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or inability to cure them, but for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his own Glory, who therefore carries them as perpetual badges of his own Victory and Triumph.<note place="margin">S. Aug. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>49.</hi> quaſi ſi quiſquam vir fortis pro patria dimicans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> As if ſome valiant Man, who had received Wounds in the War for his Country, having a Skilful Chirurgeon that could cure them without Scars, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him ſo to cure them, that the Scars might remain as Badges of the ſervice he had done his Country.<note place="margin">Leo. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> de aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Dom. ut non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biâ fide, ſed conſtantiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſcientia teneretur eam natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram in Dei Patris con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſuram throno, quae jacuerat in Sepulchro.</note> The Scars would Chriſt have to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main alſo, that hereby the Hearts of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples might be confirmed in the Faith of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; and therefore ſhowing them to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Be not faithleſs, but believing.</hi> And this is ſo ordered (ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi>) that the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, at the day of Judgment, may hence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how juſtly they have the Sentence paſſed upon them, when they ſhall ſee him whom they have pierced. Of the humane Soul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united to his Body, he gave Evidence, after he aroſe, by the Operations of it. This reality
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58299:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Chriſt's Reſurrection in the very ſame nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Body which was Crucified and Buried, with the ſame humane Soul united unto it, which did before animate it, is well expreſſed, by our Church,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Angl. Art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> in the Book of Articles in theſe words, <hi>Chriſt did truly riſe again from death, and took again his Body with Fleſh and Bones, and all things appertaining unto the perfection of Man's nature.</hi> In which laſt words we are taught how his humane Soul was united to the ſame nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Body which had been laid in the Grave; this in a ſpecial manner belonging to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the humane nature.</p>
            <p>This real Reſurrection did Chriſt effect by his own power, as the Text ſhows, and the Scriptures foretold; for the Scriptures did not only foretel, that he ſhould <hi>be raiſed</hi> from the dead, but that he ſhould <hi>Riſe</hi> again from the dead, which ſhows it to be <hi>his own Act.</hi> When the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>He ſhall lift up the head,</hi> it is to the ſame ſenſe as thoſe words of his own, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and I will raiſe it up again.</hi> This was the Evidence (and a ſufficient one) that he was the <hi>true Meſſiah,</hi> the Son of God, and Saviour of the World. But then it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that this was not after the <hi>Socinian</hi> Mode, who hold, that God the Father raiſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58299:12"/>Chriſt to Life, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> being reſtored to Life, did lift and raiſe his Body out of the Grave, as the Man ſick of the Palſie raiſed himſelf from the Bed, or as we ſhall raiſe our ſelves out of our Graves at the ſound of the laſt Trump. And they tell us, this was all that Chriſt could do; but if this was all, <hi>Chriſt</hi> might as well have ſaid, Deſtroy this Temple, and any one of you may raiſe it up; for when <hi>God</hi> had reſtored life unto it, any one of them might have lifted it up, and raiſed it out of the Grave, and have ſhewed it alive. We deny not but ſometimes in Scripture the Reſurrection of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Father, and ſometimes to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, but it is alſo attributed to himſelf, who, as he freely laid down his Life for us, ſo did he, <hi>by his own Power,</hi> raiſe it up again; he was not only paſſive in it, but active: Nor let any object and ſay, What then needed the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel to be ſent before to roll away the Stone, if he could raiſe himſelf out of the Grave?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſol. Serm. 75.</hi> Angelus revolvit lapidem, non ut egredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti Domino praeberet aditum, ſed ut Dominum mundo jam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrexiſſe monſtraret: conſervis ad credendum daret fidem, non ad reſurgendum Domino praeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret auxilium.</note> for the Stone was not rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away, by the Angel, ſo much to give his Body paſſage out, as to give his Diſciples paſſage into the Grave, to behold the reality of his Reſurrection; otherwiſe, he who came in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58299:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>while the door was ſhut, could as well have came out while the Grave was ſhut. <hi>Elizeus</hi> raiſed another, not himſelf: the Apoſtles rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed others, yet cannot raiſe themſelves:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Bern. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> de Feſto Sanctae Paſchae.</note> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> raiſed himſelf by his own power, which ſhews the Excellency of his Reſurrection above the Reſurrection of others. By all which you ſee our ſecond point fully cleared, that as the Scripture had foretold Chriſt ſhould riſe, ſo did Chriſt really riſe, and in the ſame manner.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We have one point more, <hi>That there was a neceſſity Chriſt ſhould thus riſe from the dead;</hi> intimated in the word <hi>muſt.</hi> For ſo the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures did declare, not only that there was a conveniency that he ſhould riſe, that it may be he would riſe, it may be not, but <hi>that he muſt riſe again from the dead.</hi> Beſides, the fulfilling of all the Scriptures foretelling it, a double ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity there was of Chriſt's riſing from the dead, namely, in reſpect of himſelf, and in reſpect of us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of himſelf, it was neceſſary, that hereby he might evidence himſelf to be the true Meſſiah, who was to come, and no Impoſtor, as the Jews blaſphemed. This was a ſpecial ſign of him who was to be the true Meſſiah, and therefore when the Phariſees cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58299:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon him for a Sign, he inſtanced in his Reſurrection, which was enough to convince them; and from hence Saint <hi>Peter</hi> draws his Concluſion,<note place="margin">Act. 2.36.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore</hi> (namely, becauſe he hath raiſed him from the dead) <hi>let all the Houſe of Iſrael know, that God hath made that ſame Jeſus both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> Part of the office of Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, was Executed on Earth, but part thereof was to be Executed in Heaven; he ought to be Prieſt, Prophet, and King, not only a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while here on Earth, but for ever, his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was to be an Everlaſting Kingdom; now, in order to the execution of that part of his office of Mediatorſhip which was to be done in Heaven, neceſſary was it that he ſhould riſe from the dead.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This was neceſſary in reſpect of us, were it but to remove from us the ſcandal of the Croſs. Unto the Greeks nothing ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ridiculous, than that men ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to rely upon a Crucified Chriſt for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and to the Jews this was a great ſtumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-block: how could this great offence, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from his ignominious death, be removed, had he not roſe from the dead? Religion had been left in a bad caſe, if Chriſt had not riſen. The Gentiles Religion, at that time, was no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58299:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>better than Irreligion: the Jewiſh Religion was now grown ſuch a Yoke and Burden, that the World grew weary of it, and 'twas thought by the wiſeſt, that it was high time there ſhould be an end of that Yoke: ſo that, had not Chriſt riſen, the Chriſtian Religion, which was now to be the ſtanding Religion, had been but tottering, and all the Profeſſors of the ſame would have ſneaked away when they ſaw the Founder of their Religion conquered by death, and not able to riſe again. Had not Chriſt riſen, our Faith and Preaching had been in vain. What profit had there been in his Blood if he had not riſen? Surely none, but we had ſtill been in our ſins; that therefore the coſt of his Blood might not be in vain unto us, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary was it that he ſhould riſe again. As alſo that we might have a teſtimony of the Father's ſatisfaction. Chriſt undertook to be Man's Surety, to diſcharge his Debts, and thus made himſelf the Debtor (as you heard very well explained laſt <hi>Friday</hi>) ſo long as the Debtor is in Priſon, it is a ſign the Debt is not ſatisfied: therefore, that we might be aſſured the Debt is fully ſatisfied, the Priſoner muſt be let out, Chriſt muſt riſe, the Surety being ſet at liberty, now we are begotten unto a lively hope by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58299:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Reſurrection of <hi>Chriſt</hi> from the dead. And neceſſary it was <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould riſe, as the firſt fruits of our Reſurrection, in which reſpect one of the Fathers well calls Chriſt,<note place="margin">Juſt. Mart. Q. &amp; Reſp. ad Graec. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Lev. 23.10.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The Captain of our Reſurrection,</hi> leading the way to us that are to follow. The Law concerning the Firſt-fruits is ſet down in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> in which we may obſerve, that the lifting up the Sheaf before the Lord, did note Chriſt's riſing out of the Grave: and, as thoſe Fruits had the name of Firſt-fruits, becauſe they were the firſt that were gathered; ſo was Chriſt the firſt that roſe from the dead, the firſt that roſe in Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the firſt that roſe unto preſent participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Glory:<note place="margin">S. Cyp. lib. de reſur. Dom. Juſt. Mart. Q. &amp; R. ad orthod. q. <hi>85.</hi> Bern. Ser. <hi>1.</hi> de feſto S. Paſch.</note> for all who, we read, were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before him, did die again to take a larger Draught of that Cup they had before but ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of: ſo that their Reſurrection was imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and incompleat, but Chriſt was the firſt that ever roſe by a full, compleat, and perfect Reſurrection unto the preſent participation of Glory. But that is not all, the Firſt-fruits had a ſpecial reference unto all the reſt, ſo that all the Sheafs in the Field were holy by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of that; and in that Chriſt is ſaid to be the Firſt-fruits of them that ſlept; it ſhews, that he roſe for us, that our duſt might be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58299:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſanctified, our Mortality conſecrated to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Chriſt's Reſurrection hath an influence upon us in order to a twofold Reſurrection; a Reſurrection from the Grave of Sin unto the Life of Grace, and to the Reſurrection of our Bodies; for, beſides, that it is a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the poſſibility of our riſing (the ſame power that raiſed Chriſt, being able to raiſe us) it hath the influence of an efficient cauſe upon our Reſurrection, he riſing not as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon, but as a publick Principle; if the <hi>Head</hi> be raiſed, the <hi>Members</hi> ſhall alſo riſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>INFERENCES.</head>
               <p>If Chriſt be riſen, according as the Scriptures declared there was a neceſſity he ſhould, then will he undoubtedly come to Judgment; for why roſe he, but to receive all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth. Know this,<note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note> 
                  <hi>That God hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the World by him, whom he hath raiſed from the dead.</hi> Than which nothing can be more terrible to ſuch who are the Enemies of Chriſt, and lead an ungodly Life; he whom Death and Hell could not hold, how ſhall any thing hold him from revenging himſelf to the full, upon ſuch who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58299:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be found his Enemies? If he were in the Grave, then you might ſwear and curſe, and be intemperate and unclean, and break all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, dreaming of Impunity; but conſider, O Chriſtians, 'tis not a dead but a living Chriſt you thus diſhonour, who will come to call you to an Account; who, as he will be a bountiful Rewarder of them that ſerve him, ſo will he be a moſt powerful Revenger of the Injuries offered him!</p>
               <p>We will not enlarge upon ſo ſad a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation at this time, 'tis a day of Joy, and much comfort is there in Chriſt's Reſurrection, eſpecially to thoſe who believe in his Name. If on any day you lift up your ſelves with Joy, then on this day when Chriſt did riſe, and lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up his Head out of the Grave, the Jubilees in old time were the Figures of the Joys in this acceptable time; for by the Reſurrection of Chriſt every true Believer is ſet free from the hands of his Enemies, his Treſpaſſes forgiven, he is reſtored again to his intereſt in that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Poſſeſſion which was loſt in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of <hi>Adam.</hi> Here is comfort againſt the fear of Death; how may you triumph over Death and the Grave? <hi>O Death, where is thy Sting? O Grave, where is thy Victory?</hi> Aſſure
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58299:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>your ſelves, Death can have no Victory over you.<note place="margin">Tertull. lib. de Reſur. Caro ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth excellently and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably treat upon this point. <hi>The Body</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is as it were the Hinge of Salvation;</hi> as we ſee in Baptiſm, <hi>the Fleſh is waſhed</hi> and ſprinkled with Water, that <hi>the Soul</hi> may be cleanſed. And when the Holy Ghoſt was given by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, the <hi>Body</hi> was ſhadowed by laying on of hands, that the Soul might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened with the Holy Ghoſt. Thus in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, <hi>the Body</hi> eats and drinks the Bread and Wine, Chriſt's Body and Blood Sacramentally, that <hi>the Soul</hi> may feaſt upon Chriſt, and be ſatisfied. It cannot therefore be imagined (as the ſame Father well argues) that the Body and Soul being thus joined in the Acts of Religion, ſhould be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the Reward. Nay, we may further take notice, that where the work of Grace is truly wrought, the whole Man is renewed, the Body as well as the Soul; ſo then, if the Body be not raiſed, the new Man ſhould be deſtroyed, the Soul alone not making the new Man, but in conjunction with the Body. Suffer not therefore any to ſhake or unſettle you in this great Foundation-Doctrine of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Though Heathens and Epicures may
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58299:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>laugh at this as an old Wifes Fable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Min. Fel. Oct. de id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vanit.</note> though Atheiſts and Hereticks may ſcoff at it as a Childiſh Vanity and Madneſs; yet, be not ſhaken, though it be a Doctrine above reaſon, it is not againſt reaſon. The Apoſtle ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues before King <hi>Agrippa, Why ſhould it be thought a thing unreaſonable with you, that God ſhould raiſe the dead?</hi> God's word muſt be made good, for he is as infallible in his word as in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; now, his word is, <hi>That all who are in the duſt ſhall awake, and all that are in the Grave ſhall hear Chriſt's Voice, and come forth.</hi> As for thoſe who talk of I know not what Vehicle of the Soul, to which it ſhall be then joined at the great day, other than the Body, in which it here dwelt in this World, and which is laid in the Grave, it is not only contrary to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but to the Doctrine of the ancient Church<note n="*" place="margin">Epiphan. cont. Haereſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi> item in lib. Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. fuſè. Aeneas Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaeus Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt. Tertull. lib. de Reſurr. cap. <hi>56.</hi> Dion. Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarch. lib. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> , which conſtantly teach, that the ſame Body which is laid in the Grave ſhall be raiſed, which can no way be ſaid of that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined Vehicle, which never was in the Grave. For your farther confirmation, conſider the point of Juſtice and Equity, if it doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that there ſhould be a Reſurrection of the dead, in the very ſame numerical Bodies, for how elſe ſhould every one be rewarded
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58299:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>according to his Works? How can it ſtand with the rule of Juſtice, that one Body ſhould ſerve God, and ſuffer for God, and another Body ſhould be rewarded; that one Body ſhould Sin, and another Body ſhould be damn'd? As Chriſt did riſe in the ſame Body which died, ſo ſhall all men riſe <hi>in their own Bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many indeed are the vain Scruples of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Spirits againſt this Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body, as, how it is poſſible,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>This is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by</hi> Aeneas Gazaeus, <hi>in his</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus. <hi>By</hi> Juſtin. Mart. Q. &amp; R. ad Graecos. <hi>In alſo</hi> Q. &amp; R. ad orthod. q. <hi>3.</hi> Athenag. de reſur. p. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> when crumbled into duſt, and one Man's duſt mixed with another; nay, it may be, one Man devoured by another, and turned into his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: How it is poſſible, that a Man being eaten by Fiſhes, thoſe Fiſhes again eaten by Men; that after ſo many mutations, changes, mixtures, alterations of Mens Bodies, they ſhould be raiſed the very ſame Bodies, and every one have his own Body? But if you be Chriſtians who have ſuch thoughts, give me leave to ask you what the firſt Article of your Chriſtian Faith is: Is it not this? <hi>That God is Almighty?</hi> If you believe this, it will be eaſy to believe the Reſurrection of the dead after never ſo many changes, ſince that to Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency all things are poſſible. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. de Civ. Dei. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi> quanto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtius cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti ſemel animas ad corpora pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria, quam reverti to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa?</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58299:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Doctrine concerning the riſing of the ſame Body, is far more reaſonable than their Opinion who held tranſmigration of Souls, or the paſſing of Souls into ſeveral Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> argues.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould we deny that power to God, which we ſee, (in a manner) in the Creature? Lay a heap of all ſorts of duſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Duſt of Gold, Silver, Tinn, Wood, Iron, apply the Loadſtone to this heap of duſt, and it will ſever the Duſt of the Iron from all the reſt, and draw it to it ſelf: and ſhall we not believe, that God can know every Man's peculiar Duſt, and ſeparate it from the reſt, yea, and raiſe it up to Heaven? Look again into Nature, and you may ſee enough to ſtrengthen your Faith in the Reſurrection of the dead. Conſider the daily Reſurrections in the World, and you may ſee our Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhadowed in the Day and Night: The Sun ſets and riſeth again; ſee you not the Fruits of the Field, Herbs, Plants, Trees? do they not die, as it were in the Winter, and live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the Spring?<note place="margin">Theoph. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch. Antioch. ad Autol. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> doth not the Corn Men ſowe, die and riſe again? <hi>Theophilus</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> follows this Argument at large.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58299:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Amb. Hexaem. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> and ſeveral others of the ancients urge the <hi>Phoenix</hi> to prove the Reſurrection; which inſtance is ſo common, I need not ſpend time in relating it. Let us obſerve the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God in our ſelves, and we ſhall have no cauſe to doubt the Reſurrection of our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Conſider of what a ſmall beginning, at our Conception, God raiſeth ſo goodly a Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture as our Bodies, and you muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him able to raiſe them again. Nay, of what did God make Man at firſt? Did he not make us of nothing? Now, conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be an act of greater power to raiſe a Body at the laſt day, of ſome matter yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, or at firſt to make it of nothing. Therefore, with <hi>Polycarp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Polyc. Ep. ad Philip.</note> we may look upon him who denies the Reſurrection of the dead, as <hi>the firſt begotten, and eldeſt Son of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Enemies need Believers fear, if Chriſt be riſen? He that was too hard for Death, will be too hard for any of your Enemies. He who hath overcome the great <hi>Goliah</hi> for you, can he not overcome the <hi>leſſer Philiſtins?</hi> What Calamities or Miſeries can you fall into, but you may fetch comfort out of Chriſt's Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to ſupport you under them? He that raiſed himſelf from the dead, hath power to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58299:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>deliver us from all evil. This was <hi>Job</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in all his Afflictions, the ſumm of whoſe Argument is this, <hi>God will raiſe me up at the laſt day,</hi> therefore undoubtedly he is able (if it ſtand with his own Glory, and my good) to lift me up from this Dunghil again.</p>
               <p>Have you parted from Believing Relations? there is no reaſon to mourn as thoſe without Hope, ſince Chriſt is riſen, and will raiſe them again to Life. And why ſhould we trouble our ſelves over-much at the Frailty and Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of theſe Bodies? Chriſt is riſen, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture, and this corruptible ſhall put on Incorruption, this mortal ſhall put on Immortality.</p>
               <p>To conclude all, Is Chriſt riſen? Let us every one look into our ſelves, and ſee what power the Reſurrection of Chriſt hath had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Hearts. Riſen he is, but is he riſen in our Hearts? What ſhare have we in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? Good Chriſtians feel the power of his Reſurrection quickening them unto Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If we can truly ſay, he hath quickened us together with Chriſt, that would be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe. There is a Reſurrection of Souls here, and of Bodies hereafter; 'tis the Reſurrection of our Souls here from the death of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58299:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sin unto the Life of Grace, that is, the Fruit of Chriſt's Reſurrection in all who are for Eternal Happineſs. He that hath part in this firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, the ſecond Death ſhall have no power over him. Let us learn to live as thoſe who believe Chriſt's Reſurrection, ſeeking thoſe things that are above, where Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God. It is the moſt unbecoming Frame for a Chriſtian to be Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded; for a Man to be graſping after the World; to have his Heart ſet upon his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, to be loading himſelf with thick Clay, to be ſtill crying, <hi>Give, give,</hi> never to be contented with theſe outward things, with the Hog to be rooting in the Dunghil, and wallowing in the muck and mire of the World; Is this to live as becometh one who profeſſeth himſelf to be riſen with Chriſt? No aſſuredly. If we be Chriſtians, let us not inordinately mind theſe things, let our Hearts be where our Head Chriſt Jeſus is, let us ſeek the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Chriſt hath prepared for us. For our Hearts to be panting after Chriſt as the Hart panteth after the water Brooks, every day to have our ſet times of Communion with God and Chriſt, to be angry at what ever draws our Hearts aſide from Heavenly things, to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58299:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>frequent in Holy Contemplations, pondering in our thoughts the weightineſs of that Crown of Glory prepared for us, to be in daily long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expectations of the coming and appearing of our bleſſed Saviour; this is to live as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thoſe who believe Chriſt is riſen, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture: To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:58299:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Mr <hi>Hesketh</hi>'s Piety, the beſt Rule of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>— 's Serious Exhortation to frequent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>— 's Caſe of Communicating unworthily, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>The Faith and Practice of a Church of <hi>England</hi> Man. The third Edition, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Religion the Perfection of Man, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>An Expoſition on the Church Catechiſm. By way of Queſtion and Anſwer, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stainforth</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1688/9. at <hi>York.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Lynford</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor, <hi>Feb.</hi> 24. 1688/9.</item>
               <item>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Scott</hi>'s Sermon at the late Lord Mayor's Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, <hi>March</hi> 27. 1689.</item>
               <item>The Oration of <hi>Cicero</hi> for <hi>M. Marcellus,</hi> done into Engliſh. With an Appendix relating to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
